我已经活了那么多年
I have lived through many ages ...
我变成过鲑鱼
through the eyes of salmon,
鹿
deer,
还有狼
and wolf.
我看到了北方人侵略爱尔兰 寻找黄金
I have seen the North Men invading Ireland\ndestroying homes, in search gold.
我看到了黑暗中的煎熬和苦难
I have seen suffering in the darkness,
然而 我在最脆弱的地方\n看到了美丽的希望
yet ... I have seen beauty\nthrive in the most fragile of places.
我看到了那本书\n那本将黑暗变为光明的书
I have seen the book ... the book\nthat turned darkness into light.
片名：凯尔斯的秘密
The Secret of Kells 2009
布兰登！别让它跑了！
Brendan? Don't let her get away!
来吧 漂亮的小鹅鹅
Come on! Nice goosy, goosy, goosy ...
靠后点 我来搞定
Stand back, I will get her!
哪边？
Which way?
布兰登 那个支架还不牢固
Brendan! That scaffolding is not steady!
别担心 阿索尔修士 我会小心的
Don't worry, brother Assoua, I'll be careful.
不好意思
Sorry.
布兰登！
Brendan!
来了
Coming!
布兰登！
Brendan!
你受伤了吗？
Are you hurt?
让它安静点 布兰登\n否则修道院长会听到的
Keep it quiet, Brendan!\nOr the abbot will hear.
我很抱歉 但是我必须要这么做\n很快就会完事的
I'm sorry, but we have to do this.\nIt will all be over in a minute.
1…2…3…4…5\nOne…Two…Three…Four…Five
也不是很疼 对吧
Now, that wasn't so hard, was it?
幸运的小鸟
Lucky bird.
你的羽毛将成为\n我们书写那些不朽篇章的工具
Your feathers will become the tools\nfrom which we create immortal pages\nof sacred text.
院长 请听我解释
Abbot! I explain for you ...
我们想抓住这只鹅 但是它跑的太快了
We tried to catch goose ... \nand she run very fast.
我跌到了泥里
And I fall in the mud ...
原谅我们吧 院长
Forgive us, abbot.
布兰登 我要的设计图在哪？
Brendan! Where are those\nplans I asked for?
设计图？我忘在书房了
The plans ... I left them in the\nscriptorium.
- 把它们拿到塔楼来\n- 是的 叔叔
- Bring them to the tower\n- Yes uncle.
明天你们回去继续修建城墙\n从早干到晚
Tomorrow, you will go back to work on the wall.\nDawn t'll evening bell.
然后你 里昂纳多修士
and brother Leonardo ...
回去清洗一下 可怜人
... clean yourself up for pity's sake.
我不知道为什么我们艺术家也要被征用\n他就只关心那墙吗？
I do not know why there are at it this intense\nwhen all that man wants us to do is to build his crazy wall.
没错 其他事他都不关心\n不过你却一直在替他辩护 布兰登
Yes, that's all the man cares about, nothing else,\nand you continue to defend him, Brendan!
叔叔只是想抵挡外面的侵略
Uncle just wants to protect us from outside.
北方的维京人来入侵的时候\n他们不管老少 所以
When the North Men come to Kells, they'll make no distinction\nbetween young and old. So ...
做好准备或者准备受死吧
"Prepare or meet your doom!"
你们就是不明白…
You just don't understand ...
但是布兰登 你从来没有到这墙外去过
But Brendan, you've never been outside these walls.
但是我不用出去也知道外面有多危险
I don't have to go outside to know how dangerous it is.
- 你去哪了？\n- 去弄这个了 给你的
- Where have you all been?\n- We went to get these, for you.
你真应该看看谢尔盖修士
You should have seen brother Sergey,
它的羽毛一伸展开\n就像一只美丽的天鹅
he took a flying dive,\nlike a beautiful swan.
这一点也不好笑
It is not funny.
修道院长看到我们了 他不开心\n因为我们没有在墙上干活
The abbot has seen us, he is not happy\nbecause we are not work on the wall.
够了 那书呢？没人看重它们吗？
Now enough of that! What about the books?\nDoes he not find them?
如果没有书\n所有的知识都会流逝 永远的流逝
If there were no books, all knowledge\nwould be lost ... for ethernity.
我们不能永远指望建造城墙！
We cannot only build walls.
人们需要读书 这样才有希望
The people must have books,\nso that they may have hope.
如果我们有本真正绘经大师的书 \n那对我们的工作会有很大帮助
If we had a true master illuminator\nwould would do so much splendid work!
让我们祈祷上帝有一天会给我们带来
Let us pray that one will be delivered to us\none day.
对 我们一起祈祷
Let us Pray!
你当然不需要一个大师\n你们的作品是我见过最漂亮的了
Surely you don't need a master,\nyour work is the finest I've seen ...
谢谢你 布兰登\n但是我们离真正的大师还是有差距的
Thanks Brendan, but\nwe are mere scriblers...
真正的大师？比方说？
- next to true masters.\n- True masters? Such as ...
比方说 艾奥纳的伊丹修士
Brother Aidan of Iona.
伊丹的确是很棒的
He is indeed the great one.
伊丹修士是谁啊？
Who is the brother Aidan?
一个很有智慧的人
A sage.
最有智慧的人
The wisest one of them all.
最完美的绘经师
The perfect Illuminator.
那伊丹在哪？
Well where is he then?
他住在一个叫艾奥纳的小岛上
He lives on a tiny island called Iona.
那里有一座寺庙 他在那里\n绘制一部了不起的书 艾奥纳之书
There is an abbey on the island, where he works\non a magnificent book: The Book of Iona.
那本书是200年前 由圣人科伦巴努写的
The book was begon 200 years ago, under the\norders of none other than Saint Columb Kil himself.
艾奥纳之书远远超过其他的书籍
The Book of Iona outshines\nall others
因为科伦巴努第三只眼睛创造的奇迹
because of the miracle of \nColumb Kil's third eye
不是因为他的第三只眼睛\n是因为他有三只长了十二个指头的手
No, not because of his third eye, because of his\nthree hands with 12 fingers on each.
不不不 他有三只眼睛 不是三只手
That's not true! He had a third eye,\nnot a third hand!
你没听说过他的科伦巴努之眼吗？
Have you not heard of the eye\nof Columb Kil ?
我当然听过\n但那第三只眼睛是用来预测未来的
Ofcourse! But that was for \nmaking the prophecies
是他的第三只手开始写的这本书
His third hand was \nfor beginning the book.
够了！跟我说说关于伊丹修士的事
Enough! Just tell us about\nBrother Aidan.
他在绘经 然后书上发出了光芒\n然后他就消失了
His writings are said to glow from the pages,\nas though they are light.
有罪的人看了书页 眼睛就瞎掉了
Sinners have been blinded\nwhile glansing upon the pages.
书页上的语言看起来像天堂自身
For to gaze upon the book, is to gaze\nupon the heavons itself!
艾奥纳之书
The Book of Iona.
但是艾奥纳在哪呢？
But where is Iona?
在很遥远的海上\n像所有其他的小岛一样
It is far far away in the sea. Like all\nislands should be.
一个世外桃源
A beautiful place
一个绘经师不用住在城墙里的地方
where the illuminators\ndo not have to build walls.
但是院长说小岛会很容易遭到攻击
But the abbot sais that\nislands are too easy to attack.
布兰登！你怎么还在这里？
Brendan! Are you still here?
赶快拿上院长的设计图\n否则你就有麻烦啦
You'd better bring the abbot those plans,\nor you'll be in big trouble!
叔叔！
Uncle!
快点！孩子！
Hurry boy!
我拿来了 叔叔
Here they are uncle.
布兰登！你一再的让我失望\n让我怎么还能相信你的责任心
Brendan! How am I to trust you with responsablity\nwhen you continue to disappoint me?
总有一天你会掌管这修道院
One day you will take controle of this Abbey.
但今天这么简单的事\n你却你花了几个小时
Yet it takes you several hours to fulfill\na simple task.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
修士们在讨论艾奥纳\n我梦到它被摧毁了
The monks were talking about Iona.\nI dreamt it was destroyed.
那个梦好真实 叔叔
It was so real uncle!
那的确是真的 布兰登
It is real Brendan.
总有一天 灾难也会降临到这里
One day that horror will come to us.
这正是为什么我们要做好准备
That is exactly why we must prepare\nourselves.
这面墙一共有三个支柱\n分别是：这里 这里和这里
This section of the wall is supported by\nthree pillars: here, here and here.
叔叔 有人来了
Uncle, someone has arrived!
他有只白猫
He has a white cat!
毫无疑问肯定又是一个\n维京人屠杀的受害者
Another victim of the North Men no doubt.
现在 我们来看
Let's see.
怎么会？比非洲还远？
* crowd talking *
不不不 没有那么远\n但是我们都是徒步走的
Oh, no, no ... not that far.\nBut we've legs walked ourselves all the way.
但是 拜托\n究竟是从哪来的？很远的地方吗？
But please, from where?\nA very long way?
不是 也没那么长
Oh yes, it was long enough alright.
有这个小家伙跟着 时间就过得快一倍了
but when you just want to keep up with,\nthe road just takes half the time.
我说的对不？潘戈邦？
Isn't that right Pangur Ban?
欢迎来到凯尔斯 修士
Welcome to Kells, brother.
- 卡拉院长！\n- 和平与你同在！
- Abbot Cellach\n- Peace be with you!
修士们 请欢迎我们这个时代\n最杰出的绘经师
Brothers,  welcome to Kells\none of the great illuminators of our times.
肯定忘了谁了
Must be a mistake.
来自艾奥纳的 伊丹修士
Brother Aidan of Iona.
大家一次问一个问题好吗
One question at a time.
就像科伦巴努经常说的\n“问题憋着不烧舌头”
As Columb Kil used to say: "Questions do not burn\nyour tongue if you wait to ask them"
欢迎来到凯尔斯 伊丹修士
Welcome to Kells, brother Aidan!
这边走 来吧
Just this way, brother.
你好 欢迎来到凯尔斯
Hello! Welcome to Kells!
等等
Hey, wait!
说说你和那本书的事吧
just talking of you and of the book.
真不错的房间 不是吗！
Fine size of a place, isn't it?
新鲜流动的空气 明亮的光线\n真的很不错
Good clean air, bright light coming\nfrom those windows ...
修士！
Brother!
那是你保护书的方法吗？
Is that where you keep the book?
Is ... that where... you keep... the..
请问你是哪位？\n是个小个子的修士 我看出来了
And who might you be?\nA very short brother I see.
虽然个子小 问题却不小
Although short of stature is never as short\nof questions.
但你为什么这么关心书的事呢
And of what interest is the book to you?
呃 修士们都在讨论\n他们说圣人科伦巴努…
Well ... the brothers where talking, and they said\nthat Saint Columb Kil himself began s...
修士们 既然伊丹修士来了\n那就让他看看凯尔斯的加强工作
Brothers, the brother of Aidan\nmust come with me.  I must take him to see the important work\nwe are doing to fortify Kells.
你还有很多事情要做
You all have work to do.
那份设计图在我的办公室
The plans are in my work room.
- 我觉得我可以待在这…\n- 这边走 修士
- Ah see, I was thinking, I could stay here\nand ... -Right this way, brother.
孩子！找点吃的来给…
Lad! Find some food for a...
你看 我下决心在两年时间完成这个工作
You see, I am determined to complete the fortifications\nwithin two years.
那么你就是潘戈邦喽 我是布…
So, you're Pangur\nBan. Well I'm Bre ...
喂 等等 我是负责喂你的
Hey! Wait! I'm supposed to feed you
等等
Wait!
潘戈邦！
Pangur Ban!
你不应该来这 维京人会跟来的
You shouldn't have come here.\nThe North Men will have followed...
那我就站着等死？
"Did I have to stay, to be killed?
我跑了很远 把他们甩掉 卡拉修士
I escaped the Vikings and left them far behind.\nBrother Cellach
我的意思是 卡拉院长
Sorry, I mean ... abbot Cellach.
书很安全 我需要把它完成
The book is saved, and I need to completed.
没错 但我们这里有更重要的要完成
Yes, well ... we have more pressing things \nto complete here.
- 你是指你的墙？\n- 不是“我的”墙！
- You mean your wall?\n- Not my wall, Aidan!
是保护文明社会的墙
A wall to save civilization.
是拯救你那本书的墙
A wall to save your book!
异教徒…
Pagens ...
克鲁姆的崇拜者们
Crom worshipers...
我们的墙的坚固\n会让他们知道我们的信念有多坚定
It is with the strenght of our walls, that they will \ncome to trust the strenght of our faith.
反正 我只擅长绘经 卡拉
You were always good at the old drawing, Cellach.
是的 如果不介意的话\n我还有很多事要做
Yes, well if you'd excuse me... \nI have a lot to attend to.
没有墙能阻挡维京人的进攻
No wall can stop the North Men, abbot.
当他们来时 我们能做的只有逃跑
When they come, all we can do is run
并且祈祷我们跑的足够快
and hope that\nare we're fast enough.
走吧 潘戈
Come on Pangur.
潘戈！
Pangur!
我不会让书受到任何损伤的
I don't mean the book any harm.
我所见过的都是凯尔斯内的书
All I've ever seen is inside the walls of Kells.
我就看一张就行
If I could just see one page
求你了
Please.
好吧
Well!
这不是那个有大问题的小朋友吗？
If it isn't the little brother with\nthe big questions?
- 我不是有意…\n- 我懂
- I didn't mean to ...\n- I understand.
你厌倦了偷听我和卡拉的谈话\n然后就跑到这里来了
You got bored eavesdropping on the abbot's private conversation\nand decided to rummed through my things.
不 不是这样的
Oh, no, that's not it!
别激动 别激动 我没有生气
Calm down lad, I won't tell on ya.
可能我…
Maybe I ...
修士们说 有罪的人看了书就会变成瞎子
The brothers said that sinners are\nblinded if they glassed at the book.
所以我还是不要看了…
So maybe I shouldn't
你真认为会这样？
Is that what you really believe what happened?
生活充满了疑问 是不是？
There's nothing in this life but mist, is there lad?
这是你自己的决定 不是别人的
It's your decision, no one else's.
真正宝贵的不是封面 打开它
The cover is not the real treasure. Open it!
天使之作
The work of angels.
“天使之作” 潘戈邦 你听到了没？
"The work of the angels"\nDid you hear that, Pangur?
我不知道天使会不会和我看起来一样有趣
I didn't know that angels would be\nas funny looking as me.
或许这个男孩真的失明了
Maybe it's the boy has gone blind.
我第一次看到它的时候也这么想
I thought the very same,\nwhen I first saw it.
但那仅仅是层皮囊 就像你和我一样
But it is only the work of\nmere mortals I'm afraid, like me or you.
这书是黑暗时代里光明的曙光
The book is a beacon in these dark days\nof the North Men.
你想不想看看最美丽的那页？
Do you want to see the most beautiful page?
能让黑暗变成光明的那页？
The one that will turn darnkess into light?
这就是神启之页
It is to be, the "Chi Ro" page.
但这里还什么也没有
But it hasn't been made yet.
没有 但它会成为整本书\n最光辉灿烂的一页
No, but it will become the most glorious page \nof the entire book.
告诉我 布兰登 你愿意帮我吗
Tell me Brendan, would you like to help?
当然 非常愿意\n我一直都在看其他修士绘经
Oh yes, please! I help the brothers\nfind quills all the time.
冷静 冷静 小修士
Calm down, calm down, little brother.
首先 你可以帮我\n在古老的橡树上收集一些这个
Now to start with, you can help me gather some of these,\nfrom an old oak tree.
这是什么
What is this?
这是个小小的普通浆果\n但可以制成你所见过的最深的翡翠绿墨水
It's a humble little berry, but it makes the \ndeepest emerald green ink you'll ever see.
如果你能帮我从树林里找来一打\n我会告诉你怎么做的 来吧
If you help me get a dozen or so from the forest\nI'll show you how to make it, so, come on!
你怎么还在这里？
What's keeping you?
我不能去 我不能到墙那边
I can't go. I'm not allowed to go outside the wall.
太危险了
It's too dangerous.
的确很危险
It is, dangerous.
在艾奥纳
Iona
我的修士兄弟在外面丧命在他们手下
I lost my brothers to attackers \nfrom the outside.
只能通过这本书来纪念他们
Now I have only the book to remember them by.
但是如果我的兄弟在这 他们会告诉你
But if my brothers where here now\nthey would tell you you'll learn more in the woods
在树林里 通过石头和树木\n可以学到的东西 比任何地方都多
from trees and rocks\nthan from any other place.
你会看到奇迹
You'll see miracles.
这是院长很久之前就知道的
And that is something the abbot knew, a long time ago.
我从来没有见过这样的东西 潘戈
I've never seen anything like it, Pangur.
我真很愿意帮助伊丹修士
I really want to\nhelp brother Aidan.
我认为我自己就可以\n弄到那些制作墨水的浆果
I think I could get\nthose ink berries all by my self.
我可以去森林\n伊丹修士肯定会很惊讶的…
I could go into the forest.\nwouldn't brother Aidan be surprised ...
但是院长…
But the abbot ...
我要在他发现之前回来
I'll be back before he'd even missed me.
但是 如果我迷路了怎么办…
But .. What if I get lost ...
在黑暗中
... in the dark?
不 我不应该出去
No! I should never go out there!
但是 如果我一直想着那本书…
if I keep thinking\nof the book
我就不会害怕黑暗了
I won't be afraid of the dark.
而且 我确定我不会天黑才回来
And I'm sure I won't have to go that far.
就这么定了 潘戈邦\n明天我就到森林里去
Alright so, Pangur Ban.\nTomorrow I'll go into the forest!
潘戈！
Pangur!
当然 如果我知道橡树长什么样就好了
Ofcourse, it might help if I knew what\nan oak tree looked like.
可能还是回去比较好…
Maybe we'd better go home...
是这条路吗？你还记得吗？
Was it this way? Do you remember?
别害怕 潘戈\n我们在天黑之前找到路就行
Don't panic, Pangur. We just have\nto find the way back before dark.
神 请帮助我吧
Ow no, it's hard enough...
这是你的猫猫吗？
Is this your cat?
好吧
Well?
我听说过 你们这种生物
I've heard about creatures like you
你是妖精 对不对？
You're a fairy!
你在我的森林里干嘛？\n你是来破坏的 对吧
What are you doing in my forest?\nYou've come to spoil it, haven't you?
你可能是你家人派来找食物的 对不对？
You were probably sent here by your family,\nto get food, weren't you?
现在你从哪儿来回哪去
Well, you can go right back where you came from.
如果不的话 我就让狼来吃了你！
If you don't, I'll make the wolves get you!
不要！
No!
我不是那个意思 你看 我很抱歉 好吗？
I didn't mean to ... Look, I'm sorry alright?
我不是来给我家人弄吃的\n我是来找做墨水的东西
I'm not here to get food for my family. \nI 'm here to get things to make ink.
我没有家人 而且我们凯尔斯里也有吃的
I don't have a family, and we\nhave food in Kells.
所以我不是为吃的而来 我只是迷路了…
So I wouldn't come here for it anyway.\nI was just a bit lost.
你没有家人？
You have no family?
没有
No.
没有妈妈？
No mother?
我也是一个人
I'm alone too.
如果这是你的森林 你肯定什么都知道
If this is your forest, you must\nknow everything about it.
当然
Well, of course.
等等
No Wait!
有人吗？
Hello?
别那么大声 快走
Shhh...not so loud! Go away!
等等 拜托 你知道哪里能弄到这个吗？
No wait Please! Do you know where\nyou can find these?
知道
Yes
但是那个是不能吃的
But you can't eat those.
我不是要吃 是要做墨水用
I don't want to eat them, they're for ink.
墨水是什么？
What is ink?
写书用的
It 's for the book ...
画图用的
For make pictures.
液体的颜色 画到纸上的
Liquid colour, you put it on pages...
就像叶子一样的…很难解释\n你有机会应该看一看
like leaves ... it's hard to explain,\nI suppose you'd have to see it.
我不知道你在说些什么\n而且我也不想知道…
I do not know what you're talking about,\nand I don't want to know ...
但是伊丹修士…
But.. brother Aidan ...
我可以帮你 但是有个条件…
I will help you find the things you want, \non one condition ...
你和你的宠物\n必须保证再也不到我的森林里来
You and your pet must promise\nto never come into my forest again.
好的 我保证
Alright then. We promise.
好吧 过来 问问森林他们在哪
Come on then, I'll ask the forest where they are.
问啥？什么？
Ask the... what ...?
嗨 等等！
Hey, wait!
我叫布兰登 你呢？
My name is Brendan. What's yours?
这是个奇迹 就像伊丹说的那样
It's a miracle, just like Aidan said.
伊丹是我的朋友
Aidan is my friend.
我在帮他书写世界上最不可思议的书
I'm helping him make the most incredible\nbook in the whole world.
会让黑暗变成光明 你等着会看到的
He sais it'll turn darkness into light.\nWait until you see it!
你等着看我另外的那片森林
Wait until you see the rest of my forest!
你跑的真快
You're fast.
是的 我是跑的最快的
Yes, I'm the fastest.
那么…
So ...
浆果在哪里？
Where are the berries then?
你以前爬过树吧？
You have climbed a tree before, haven't you?
是的 当然 小菜一碟
Yes, of course. It's easy.
那就来吧
Come on so!
我救了你的命 今天的第二次了
Saved your life, second time today.
你说过你会爬树的
I thought you knew how to climb trees.
我的确会 不过是小些的
I do. Smaller ones.
对 灌木丛而已
Yeah ... like bushes.
别往下看 快来
Don't look down. Come on!
看！
Look!
一个昆虫认出了另一个昆虫
One beatle recognizes another.
拜托！
Come on!
睁开眼睛 我告诉你我的名字
Open your eyes and I'll tell you my name.
阿诗玲
Aisling.
这 就是我的森林
and this, is my forest.
我告诉他们了 他们不会叮你的
I asked them not to sting you.
这就是你要找的果子…
Here's what you're looking for ...
但是他们算不上浆果
... but they're not really berries.
有点像野猪柿
They look like boar droppings.
闻起来也有点臭
They're kind of stinky too.
你弄完了 就要爬下去啦
If you're finished, It's time to go back down.
爬下去…
back down ...
往左边一点
A bit left.
不 等一下！别踩那个…
No wait! Don't lean on that ...
…树枝
... branch.
我很抱歉花了这么久才爬下来
I'm sorry it took so long to come down.
除了最后那一摔…
Except for the last part ...
你最好现在回去吧\n我知道一条去你家的秘密小路
We'd better go now. I know a secret way to get you home
来吧！
Come on!
看！
Look!
布兰登？
Brendan?
你在干什么？回来啊！
What are you doing? Come away!
这里是苦难之地
This is a place of suffering.
苦难？是什么意思？
Suffering? What do you mean?
只管回来吧！那里太危险了
Just come away! It's too dangerous.
肯定不会比爬大橡树还危险吧
Surely it can't be more dangerous\nthan climbing an oak tree.
这是黑暗生物的巢穴
It is the cave of the Dark One.
克鲁姆库鲁克？
Crom Cruach?
但是克鲁姆库鲁克是骗小孩的故事
But Crom Cruach's only a story for children.
凯尔斯的修道院长说\n不应该害怕虚构的东西
The Abbot of Kells, says you shouldn't\nbe afraid of imaginary things.
那不是虚构的
It's not imagined.
它在黑暗中等待着 等着有人误入歧途
It's waiting in the darkness.\nWaiting for someone to awaken it.
阿诗玲 你只是自己吓自己罢了
Aisling, you're only scaring yourself.
修道院长说 那都是异教徒的胡话
The abbot sais that that's all pagan\nnonesense.
克鲁姆库鲁克这种东西是不存在的
There's no such thing as Crom Cruach...
不要说出它的名字！
Don't... speak it's name!
你真的被吓到了？
You're really frightened?
阿诗玲！
Aisling!
你受伤了吗？
Are you hurt?
那是什么东西？
What was that?
我跟你说过了…
I told you ...
克鲁姆！
Crom!
- 布兰登？\n- 恩？
- Brendan?\n- Huh?
你可以再来森林 如果你想的话
You can visit the forest again, if you like.
潘戈邦也可以来
And Pangur can come too.
- 但是在艾奥纳我们都…\n- 这里不是艾奥纳
- But sir, on Iona we always arange them ...\n- This is not Iona.
绘经院会按我的计划安排
The scriptorium will be arranged according to \nmy instructions.
但这不是好的…
But this is not good ...
会是的 如我所说
It will be as I say.
伊丹修士！我找到了！
Brother Aidan! I found them! I...
好啊 布兰登 今天没怎么看到你
Well, Brendan. It's about time we saw you today.
你去哪儿了？
Where have you been?
我等你说呢 你去哪了？
I'm listening. Where were you?
我…
I ...
我去森林里了
I went into the forest.
只是个小森林 没去多久
Just for a little while, not very long.
是为了帮伊丹修士…
Just... It was for Brother Aidan ...
布兰登 关于墙外的世界\n难道我告诫你的还不够多吗？
Brendan. Have I not warned enough\nabout what lies beyond these walls?
- 是的 但是…\n- 然而 你却不听我话
Yet you disobey me.
我知道 但是为了书…
I know, but for the book ...
布兰登 没有我的允许\n再也不许你离开修道院半步
Brendan. You are never to leave\nthe abbey again without my permission.
但是 叔叔 如果你看了书的话…
Uncle, if you see the book ...
你听明白了吗？
Do you Understand?
是的 叔叔
Yes, uncle.
那好
Good.
那过来吧 还有很多功课要做
Now come along, there are matters to attend to\nin the workroom.
- 看！…我找到了\n- 什么？
- Look!\n- What?\n- I found them.
你找到了 你真找到了
You did? So you did!
有人帮忙才找到的…
I did have a little help.
森林里的一位朋友
From a friend in the forest.
有朋友的话\n没什么事是做不到的 对吧？
There's nothing you can't do\nwhen you have friends to help you, right?
好的 我们来瞧瞧
Now, let's see.
不错 不错 我相信这个一定能表现出色
Yes, yes ... I believe\nthese will do very nicely ...
从小小的浆果 到宏伟的图画诞生
From tiny berries do great images come to life
来吧！
Come along!
很多烟…这是个好预兆
Lot of smoke ... that's a good sign.
- 是吗？\n- 当然
- It is?\n- Yes.
- 多漂亮\n- 从一个发臭的浆果…
- Ah, beautiful.\n- From a stinky berry.
这个墨水是很棒 但还是一无是处…
Making ink is all very well, but it is useless ...
…如果缺了这个的话
... without one of these.
没有允许…我不能…
I'm not... I'm not allowed to...
这里只有我们两个人
There's no one else here now.
只有你
Just you
还有你的想象力
and your imagination.
怕了吗？
Afraid?
我？不 我才不害怕想象东西呢
Me? No. I'm not afraid of imaginary things.
接着来 有始有终
Keep going! Finish what you start.
金子！
Gold!
不错
Not bad.
要我说 你肯定有能力来做…
I'd say he could do it right enough.
做什么？
Do what?
我必须对你坦白 孩子
I must confess my boy.
我之前没有完全对你说真话
I haven't been completely honest with you.
我没法绘画那神启的一页
I can not do the Chi-ro page.
我的眼睛已经昏花 我的手也开始颤抖
My eyes have become too old.\nAnd my hands unsteady.
但是…你说…
But .. you said ...
- 你应该来画那一页！\n- 我？
- You should be the one to do that page!  - Me?
不！我肯定不行…
No! I can never...
肯定还有别的什么人可以来做！
there must be somebody else ...
还是你做好！我会做毁的
You have to do it.\nI would ruin it.
不不不 你当然做得来
No, no, no. Ofcourse you can do it.
你能找到那些浆果
You found those berries
你有一双灵巧的手
You've certainly developed a steady hand.
在我到这里之前\n你已经从别的修士那里学到了不少
Even before I came you'd already learned much\nfrom the other brothers's work.
你只需要展开你的想象力
You've only to unleash your imagination!
我该走了
I have go.
这么早你去哪里了？
Where have you been so early?
来吧 还有很多事要做
Come along, there is much work to be done.
我不知道 潘戈
I don't know Pangur...
有些我看不到的东西在阻碍着他
Something I cannot see, stops him.
如果他想完成神的一页
If he is ever to light up the Chi-ro page...
他必须转过身来 正视\n无论那是什么 面对面
he'll have to turn around and stare whatever it\nis, in the face!
布兰登！
Brendan!
我们要出发去西墙的架子了 快一点！
We're moving the scaffolding to\nthe west wall. Hurry along now!
我觉得你是时候学习科伦巴努的秘密了
I think you're ready to learn Columb Kil's secret.
那迷人的细节
The mesmerizing detail ...
当然 你还需要另一个眼睛
Of course, you need another eye.
好的
Now ...
- 当我找到那水晶的时候\n- 修士…
- Once I find the crystal...\n- Brother ...
就好象打开了一个全新的世界 \n一个纤细的世界
...open up a whole new world...\na tiny wonder...
科伦巴努说不应该用那水晶\n除非用来做最重要的作品
Columb Kil instructed that the crystal \nshould never be used, for less than work\nthat's worthy of it.
在艾奥纳就没用过
It has not been used since Iona
水晶 是什么？
What's... a crystal?
不是一个简单的水晶\n是独一无二的水晶
This's not a crystal, it's The Crystal!
科伦巴努之眼
The eye of Columb Kil.
科伦巴努 一生中创作了超过300部书
Columb Kil created over 300 books in his lifetime.
凭一己之力
By his own hands!
当他的死亡快要降临之时
On his deathbed, he prayed that his apprentice
他已经预见到那一天的到来
got a vision as clear and wonderful as his own.
而当他呼出最后一口气时…
then as he drew his last last breath ...
从他手中掉落…
it dropped from his hand ...
科伦巴努之眼
... the eye of Colomb Kil !
科伦巴努肯定也会想要你收下的
Colomb Kil would want it to go to you.
放哪了？
Where is it?
抱歉 潘戈
Sorry, Pangur.
你见过吗？
Have you seen it?
丢掉了
It's lost.
丢掉了！
It's all lost!
你最后一次见是什么时候？
Where did you last have it?
我不明白
I don't understand.
如果我能给你看看那水晶…
If I could show the crystal to you
就都明了了
all would become clear.
- 但是…\n- 但是我还是可以继续学习 不是吗？
- But ...\n- But I can still continue my training, can't I?
你学过昆虫翅膀上的细小花纹吗？
Have you ever studied the tiny pattern,\non a green fly's wing?
- 没有\n- 那没有水晶 永远也学不会了
- No.\n- And you'll never will without the crystal.
那我们祈祷奇迹发生呢？
What if we pray for a miracle?
就像科伦巴努那样的？
Like Colomb Kil did?
有人说 在那水晶\n被称为科伦巴努之眼之前
Some say, that before the crystal became known,\nas the eye of Columb Kil
还有一个古代名字
it had an ancient name.
科伦巴努就是在那里得到水晶的\n在黑暗的深处
named from the creature that\nColomb Kil won the crystal from.\nDeep inside one of it's dweling places.
克鲁姆库鲁克！
Crom Cruach!
被称为 克鲁姆库鲁克之眼
It was called the eye of "Crom Cruach"
我没法告诉你这故事哪部分是真的…
I can't tell you which parts of this story\nare true and what parts ...
哪部分又笼罩在迷雾中…
... are shrouded by the mists.
人生就是充满了那么多迷…
Ah, there's nothing in this life but mist ...
却只有短暂的时间
We're only here for a short while...
别担心 潘戈
Don't worry, Pangur.
我不会一个人的
I won't be long.
我说过禁止你离开修道院
You've been forbidden to leave the abbey.
现在我同时禁止你进入绘经院
Now you are also forbidden to enter the\nscriptorium.
拜托 叔叔 你不明白
Please, Uncle, you don't understand.
我明白的一清二楚！
Oh I understand perfectly well!
不许再私自外出
No more escorsions.
不许再绘经 不许再见伊丹修士
No more scriptorium and no more brother Aidan.
不要
No.
你刚说什么？
What did you say?
我做不到
I can't do that.
我不能放弃那书 叔叔
I can't give up the book uncle
如果你能只看一页 就明白了
If you looked at just one page and\nsee why.
你忘了那有多么重要！
You've forgotten how important it is
你所想的只有筑墙
All you want from us is this wall.
伊丹修士说你曾经也是绘经师
Brother Aidan said you were an Illuminator once.
- 他说…\n- 够了！
- He said ...\n- That's enough!
如果我不能信任你能不惹麻烦\n你就必须留在这儿 到你明白事理
If I can't trust you to stay out of harm's way\nyou'll have to remain here, untill you'll see sense.
卡拉 拜托 不要怪那孩子\n我和他谈过 而…
Cellach, please, don't blame the boy.\nI'll have a talk with to him and...
- 你不能再那么做\n- 不能…
- You do no such thing.\n- You can't ...
坦恩修士会给他送去食物\n这里也不应该有让他分心的东西
Brother Tang will bring him his meals and once\nthere is nothing left here to distract him...
让我来保管这书 卡拉
Let me keep the book Cellach.
这是托付给我的
It was entrusted to me.
那好吧
Allright then.
但条件是 当春天到来时你就离开凯尔斯
But on the condition that you leave Kells with the\nfirst sign of spring.
布兰登！
Brendan
阿诗玲！
Aisling!
我该怎么帮你出来？
How can I get you out?
我不知道
I don't know.
塔被锁上了
The tower is locked.
门被从外面锁上了
And my door is bolted from the outside.
钥匙在院长的屋子里
The key is in the abbot's room.
或许…你可以给伊丹修士送个信
Maybe ... you can take a message\nto brother Aidan.
你需去我无法到达之处
You must go where I can not ...
潘戈邦 潘戈邦
Pangur Ban ...
为什么院长把你锁在那里？
Why did the abbot put you in there?
因为我不服从他
Because I disobeyed him .
为什么？
Why?
看！
Look!
- 克鲁姆之眼！\n- 不 这是个水晶
- The Eye of Crom!\n- No, it's a crystal.
我想它在黑暗生命的洞窟里
I think there's one in the Dark One's cave.
我必须去那里
I have to go there.
不 布兰登 你被它迷惑了\n你应该留在你的塔里
No Brendan, it's tricking you.\nYou should have stayed in your tower.
克鲁姆库鲁克夺走了我的亲人\n夺走了我的母亲
Crom Cruach took my people, it took my mother.
它吞噬一切 你会死的！
It takes everything. You will die!
阿诗玲 如果我不去试的话\n书就永远无法完成了
Aisling, if I don't try, the book\nwill never be complete.
书…
The book ...
好吧 我会帮助你的…
Alright then, I will help you.
阿诗玲！这地方对你不好 你必须回去
Aisling! This place is hurting you,\nyou must go back.
我们再想其他办法
I'll find someother way.
我必须帮助你…
I.. I must help you...
拜托 阿诗玲 快回去
Please hurry, go now!
将黑暗变为 光明
Turn the darkness into light.
阿诗玲！
Aisling!
老傻瓜！
Old fools!
老傻瓜应该缄口慎言
Old fools should learn to keep quite...
除非小傻瓜想要聆听
... unless young fools want to listen ...
你来了！你是怎么…？
Ha! You're here! How ... How did you ...?
你是怎么跑出塔的？
How did you get out of the tower?
你必须在院长发现之前回去
You must go back before the abbot finds out.
这不是你该来的地方\n没什么东西给你看
This is not the place for you lad,\nthere is nothing for you here.
但是你在这儿 书在这儿
But you're here, the book is here ...
还有 眼 也在这里
and the eye is here.
这怎么可能？它已经被毁掉了
How is this possible?!\nIt was destroyed!
这眼睛的故事不止一个
There is more than one story about the eye.
黑暗生物也不止一个
There is more than one dwelling place for the Dark One ...
眼也不止一个
and he had more than one eye.
你去了黑暗生物的洞穴？
You... you entered one of the Dark One's caves?
不是所有东西都能从书上学到的 是吧
You can find out everything from books you know.
这个我可知道
I think I read that once ...
好吧 那么 是时候开始了
Right then ... it is time to begin!
您的早餐 修道院长
Your breakfast, abbot.
拿去给布兰登
Take it to Brendan.
看他是否…
See if ...
看他是否懂些事了
See if he has come to his senses.
这就像天堂
It's like heaven, no?
天堂降落到人间
Heaven on Earth.
拜托 院长 这是我的错
Please ... please abbot, it's my fault.
你这小蠢货！
Little fool!
北方人即将到来 而你在这里 绘画？
The North Men are upon us\nand here you are ... drawing!
离维京人攻击凯尔斯只有一天时间了！
We have one day before the Vikings\nattack Kells!
- 大门会挡不住的！\n- 我们必须逃离这里
- The gate won't hold.\n- We must run from here!
门会挡住他们的！\n你去把难民带进教堂
The gate will hold!\nYou will lead the refugees into the chapel.
那里应该会在攻击到来时是安全的
They will seek comfort there untill the attackers\nmove on.
坦恩 告诉村民待在家里
Tang! Tell villagers to stay in their house.
卡拉！
Cellach!
你就和你宝贵的书在这里会安全的
You'll be safe in here with your precious book.
不 还不能…
No, not yet!
待在屋里！
Stay inside!
坦恩！把门打开！
Tang! Open the door!
进塔里！
Into the tower!
一次一个人！这梯子不够牢固
One at a time!\nThe steps aren't strong enough!
太多人了
Tang, there are too many!
太晚了
It's too late.
关上门！
Close the door!
布兰登！
Brendan!
墨水！我们来做墨水！
Ink! We have to make ink!
- 布兰登！不能…\n- 快！
- Brendan! Wait... we can't ...\n- Hurry!
叔叔！
Uncle!
不！
No!
不！我们要去救他！
No! We must save him!
布兰登 去森林的密道在哪里？
Quickly Brendan, where is the\nsecret passage to the forest?
我们要去救他！
We have to save him!
我们救不了
We can't help him now.
布兰登！
Brendan!
我们不能停
We... We cannot stop.
我必须回去
I have to go back.
维京人在艾奥纳一人也不放过\n他们在凯尔斯也不会留情的
The North Men left no one on Iona,\nthey will leave no one on Kells
- 我叔叔\n- 他是为了保护你
- My uncle...\n- He lived to protect you.
用他唯一知道的方法…
The only way he knew how ...
现在 要由我来保护你
Now I must protect you
为了卡拉 也为了这本书
for Cellach and for the book.
金子！
Gold!
布兰登！
Brendan!
阿诗玲！
Aisling!
我们必须接着赶路了 布兰登\n希望我们跑得够快
We have to keep running, Brendan,\nand hope that we're fast enough.
他还活着！
He's alive!
我好累
I'm so tired.
是时候放手了
Tang, leave me be.
拜托
Please ...
不要管我了
Leave me be...
你是凯尔斯的修道院长！
You are the abbot of Kells!
你必须起来
You must get up!
书写出来不是为了藏在高墙之后…
The book was never meant to be hidden away behind walls...
是为了向世界传播 激励启发人民
... locked away from the world which inspired its creation.
布兰登
Brendan,
你要把书带给人民
You must take the book to the people
这样他们才能有希望！
So that they may have hope...
来照亮北方黑暗的日子
let it light the way in these dark days of the North Men.
阿诗玲？
Aisling?
我好累
I'm so tired.
拜托 院长 休息一下吧
Please, abbot, you must take your rest.
休息？在我们最珍贵的东西被摧毁时吗？
Rest? With our most important\ntreasure destroyed?!
但我该怎么才知道？
But how was I to know?
才知道他在何方？
How could I know he would perish?
拜托了 院长
Please, abbot.
他当时还只是个孩子
He was only a boy ...
黑暗的使者！不是现在！
Angel of Darkness! Not yet!
还不行！我需要时间！
I need time!
叔叔
Uncle!
布兰登？
Brendan?
这是梦吗？
It is a dream ...
这不是梦
This is no dream.
我那么高兴能在这儿找到你
I'm so happy to find you here.
我以为我失去了你 在很久之前
I thought I'd lost you a long ago.
布兰登
Brendan!
你当时还是个孩子
You were only a boy...
那么多无辜的人死去了…
All those innocents... lost.
- 都是我的错\n- 请别 叔叔
- All my fault...\n- Please, uncle ...
…不要责怪你自己
... Do not distress yourself.
你不明白
You don't understand.
我没有时间 布兰登
I have no time, Brendan.
你是对的
You were right ...
关于凯尔斯
About Kells ...
关于伊丹
About Aidan ...
关于书
About the book ...
我不应该…
I shouldn't have ...
这是我仅剩的了…
This is all I have left.
这是我在这世上唯一的慰籍
It is the only comfort I have in this world.
伊丹修士是对的
Brother Aidan was right ...
而我却阻止他
And I tried to stop him.
伊丹从没有怨你 叔叔
Aidan never paid you much heed, uncle.
或许吧…
I suppose not ...
伊丹修士继续着他的使命 而且完成了
Brother Aidan lived to see\nhis work passed on ... and completed.
艾奥纳之书！
The Book of Iona!
凯尔斯之书？
The Book of Kells...?
凯尔斯之书
The Book of Kells.